<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A tolleration sent down from heaven to preach, or, Godly religious meetings, and true gospell preachers, praying and preaching, in other places then parish churches and chappels, justified by the highest powers, and signally owned by testimonies from heaven, ought not to be condemned or forbiden, but rather allowed and tollerated by men upon earth and likewise what it is to preach according to the laws and statutes of the kingdome, as the matter of preaching, not punishable by the act against nonconformists : also concerning the by R.F.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18089</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12868440</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12868440</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40951)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 981:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A tolleration sent down from heaven to preach, or, Godly religious meetings, and true gospell preachers, praying and preaching, in other places then parish churches and chappels, justified by the highest powers, and signally owned by testimonies from heaven, ought not to be condemned or forbiden, but rather allowed and tollerated by men upon earth and likewise what it is to preach according to the laws and statutes of the kingdome, as the matter of preaching, not punishable by the act against nonconformists : also concerning the by R.F.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Farnworth. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94771:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94771:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TOLLERATION Sent down from Heaven to Preach. OR Godly Religious Meetings, and true Goſpell Preachers, praying and preaching, in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels, juſtified by the Higheſt Powers; and ſignally owned by Teſtimonies from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ought not to be condemned or forbiden, but rather Allowed and Tollerated by Men upon Earth. <hi>AND</hi> Likewiſe what it is to Preach according to the Laws and Statutes of the Kingdome, as to the matter of Preaching, not puniſhable by the Act againſt Nonconformiſts. <hi>ALSO</hi> Concerning the manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings, and the true Ordination of Miniſters ſent forth to Preach, according to the Scriprures, ſince Chriſts Aſſention. And likewiſe what the Goſpel is, who have a true right to preach it; and what it is for Preachers to live of the Goſpel, according to the Scriptures, or Ordination of God in that Caſe provided.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he commanded us to preach unto the people, &amp; to teſtifie that it is he which was ordained of God to be the Judge of quick and dead. To him give all the Prophets witneſs, that through his Name, whoſoever believeth in him ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive remiſſion of ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Acts 10.42,43.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Written in <hi>Gloceſterſhire</hi> the beginning of the 10<hi>th</hi> Month, 1665. By <hi>R. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94771:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94771:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Tolleration ſent down from Heaven to Preach; Or, Godly Religious Meetings, and true Goſpel Preachers, Praying and Preaching in other Places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels juſtified by the higheſt Powers, and ſignally owned by Teſtimonies from Heaven, ought not to be condemned or forbidden, but rather allowed and tollerated by Men upon Earth, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, who are made Miniſters by the Lord God of Heaven, <note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3.5,6.</note> they are by a true Spiritual right, and Goſpel authority ordained and enabled, to preach from God unto the Souls of the People, as by the Scriptures is evident and plain; therefore, ſuch ought not to be forbidden to preach, nor puniſhed for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of Man are ordained and impowered by man, and are bound to preach up the Intereſt of Man, or elſe to be turned out of their Miniſtry, &amp; maintenance by men, for refuſing the ſame: <note place="margin">Acts 10.42,43. Act. 28.30,3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Cor. 4 5.</note> But the Miniſters of God are ordained of God, and impowered by him, and bound in ſpirit to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, and the Intereſt of God; becauſe, they are not to pleaſe Men, but the Lord, nor to preach themſelves but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and themſelves (no Lords nor Maſters but) ſervants for Jeſus ſake; for they dare not make themſelves of the number, or compare themſelves with ſome that commend themſelves; for they who are ſo in love with ſelf-commendation, they do but meaſure themſelves by themſelves (or by their Schollerſhip and natural abilities) and ſo comparing themſelves amongſt themſelves, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> they are not wiſe: But the true Miniſters of Chriſt will not boaſt of things beyond their meaſure, but according to the meaſure of the rule which God hath diſtributed to them, they reach unto others in preaching the Goſpel of Chriſt, not boaſting of things beyond their meaſure; that is, of other mens labours; for not he that commendeth himſelf is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth, as by the Scriptures is evident and plain; ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12,13,14,15,16,17,18.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94771:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
They who are made able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> by him whoſe Miniſters they are, (that is to ſay by the Lord God of Heaven) and whoſe Intereſt they preach, in preaching the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, <note place="margin">Act. 28 30,31.</note> and teaching thoſe things that concern the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, no man ought to forbid them, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.30,31. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are approved by the Lord, and commended of him by their Miniſtration, to the Conſciences of Men in the ſight of the Lord as the Scriptures do teſtifie of them; for becauſe they have received a Miniſtry from God, they haye renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, not walking in craftineſs (to turn with the times for any ſelf-end) nor handling the word of God deceitfully, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.1,2,3,4,5,6,7, &amp;c.</note> but by manifeſtation of the truth, commending themſelves to every mans Conſcience in the ſight of God, as you may read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1,2,3,4,5,6,7, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt who are ordained of God, and have received a Miniſtry from him for the Peoples ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting good, they ought not to be prohibited from preaching the word of God, but are to be received as the Miniſters of God, becauſe there is great danger both in prohibiting them to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.1,2. Mat. 10.40,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1,42.</note> and alſo in rejecting them that are ſent of the Lord, and likewiſe the danger is great in receiving the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Antichriſt under pretence of the Miniſters of Chriſt; becauſe <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Joh. 4.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Joh. 1.7,8,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,10,11.</note> receive not ſuch into your houſe, neither bid them God ſpeed, leaſt ye be partakers of their evil deeds; and Chriſt himſelf ſaith concerning his Miniſters, <note place="margin">Mat. 10.7,14,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> that it ſhall be more tollerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah</hi> in the day of Judgment, then for thoſe that reject them, or refuſe to hear them preach, and deny to receive them and their Doctrine, as by the Scripture is evident and plain. Seeing then that a danger lyeth on both hands; firſt in rejecting the Miniſters of Chriſt under pretence of the Miniſters of Antichriſt; and ſecondly in receiving the Miniſters of Antichriſt under pretence of the Miniſters of Chriſt, how may they be known aſſunder? ſeeing the one hath the form as well as the other.</p>
            <p>I anſwer firſt that the Miniſters of Chriſt, who are to be received as the Miniſters of God who are rightly ordained , <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts 10.43,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 7.1,2.</note> and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Miniſtry from him, they are accompanied with a true Spiritual power, and Goſpel authority in their Miniſtration, ſo as to reach the witneſs of God in the people, who are to receive
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94771:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them, that they may be received as the Miniſter of God with the peoples conſent, without being forc'd upon them againſt their Conſciences by outward conſtraint.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <note place="margin">Mat. 10.7. 2 Cor. 4.1,2,</note> it is the part and duty of a Miniſter of Chriſt, by virtue of his office as a Miniſter, in order to his eſtabliſhment and confirmation in the hearts of the receivers of him; firſt to preach the Word of God to them; and ſecondly in preaching the Word, to commend himſelf to the conſciences of them that he preaches unto in the ſight of God that ſent him, by manifeſting the truth unto them, as a means provided by the Goſpel, for a Miniſters entrance into the people, and in order to the eſtabliſhment of him and his Miniſtry amongſt them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.18,19,20,21,22.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <note place="margin">Mat. 10 7. Act. 10.42,43.</note> the command of Chriſt to his Miniſters is to preach the Goſpel; ſecondly, All are admitted to the hearing of it, becauſe he commands to preach it to every Creature; thirdly, They are to preach it as freely as they have received it, becauſe he that hath the beſt right to ſend forth Miniſters to miniſter from him to the people, ſaith, <hi>freely ye have received, freely give;</hi> fourthly, The Miniſters of Chriſt are to preach freely, and the people are to hear them as freely, ſo that they neither ought to be hindred from preaching, nor the people from hearing. And it is the duty of a Miniſter to preach, as well as it is the duty of the people to hear, <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.21.</note> and they ought not to receive a Miniſter before they hear him, nor there is no danger if the hearers receive not a Miniſter, untill they have a true proofe and goſpel commendation of him as a Miniſter, by manifeſting truth unto them, in commending himſelf to their conſciences in the ſight of God as a Miniſter of the Goſpel of Chriſt as aforeſaid, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>chap. &amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1.2.</p>
            <p>But after God hath ordained, and ſent forth Miniſters, and given them a Miniſtry they are to attend upon it, and if men forbid them to preach, they muſt obey God rather then men; <note place="margin">Act. 4 17,18,19,20. 2 Tim. 4.1,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and in preaching the Word be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, as it is written; therefore it is the duty of the true Goſpel Miniſters to preach when they are forbidden by men, becauſe they are to preach both in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; And when is preaching the Word out of ſeaſon, but when by men it is diſlik'd and forbidden; <hi>for</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>the time will come when they will not endure ſound Doctrine, but after their own luſts ſhall they heap up to themſelves teachers, having itching ears, and they ſhall turn away their ears from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94771:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the truth, and ſhall be turned unto fables;</hi> as by the Scriptures is evident and plain, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3,4.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the Miniſters of the Goſpel are to preach, both in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, they are to continue ſtedfaſt unto God in the work of the Miniſtry; therefore they that give over prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching when men forbids them, either never received any miniſtry from God, or elſe in denying to preach, they have denyed the Lord, and thoſe are not worthy to be either heard or any more received as the Miniſters of God; therefore there is no danger in rejecting of them, becauſe they have rejected the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt are to be received after they be made manifeſt to the conſciences of the people by manifeſting the truth of the Goſpel unto them, in the ſight of him that hath ſent them, and after they be ſo manifeſt, the danger is great in rejecting of them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.7.14,15.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of God ought not to be forbidden to preach the Goſpel, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. Math. 10.7.14,15. Mat. 10.40,41,42. Mar. 6.10,11.</note> becauſe they are to be known before they be received; therefore it's neceſſary that they ſhould preach the word of God that the people may have a manifeſtation of them in order to the receiving of them, becauſe the receiving of them is as the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of God, and hath the promiſe of a great reward, and the rejecting of them (or the forbiding of them to preach) is as the rejecting of God; therefore after the Miniſter of God be made manifeſt to the conſciences of the people in the ſight of God, they ought to be received; and yet though the danger of rejecting ſuch be ſo great, the puniſhment for rejecting of them is not to be inflicted by man, but by the Lord; becauſe it ſhall be more tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorab</hi> in the day of Judgment then for ſuch: as Chriſt Jeſus hath ſaid.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt are not to be forbidden to preach, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are to commend themſelves to the Conſciences of thoſe that receives them, by manifeſting the truth of the Goſpel unto them; and as it is the Miniſters work ſo to commend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the conſciences of the people in order to reception, they ought not to be forbidden to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, becauſe preaching the Goſpel is the right way and means of manifeſting the truth unto them; and after they be made manifeſt to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the people in the ſight of God as his Miniſters; then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94771:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it's the duty of the people, <note place="margin">Rom. 10.14,15.</note> unto whoſe conſciences they are ſo made manifeſt, to receive them as the Miniſters of God, becauſe in receiving of them, it's accounted as the receiving of him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.40,41,42.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <note place="margin">Mat. 10.7.40,41,42. Mar. 6.12. 2 Cor. 7.1,2.</note> They ought to preach the Word of God, as well as they ought to be received: becauſe God commands it; and that's upon the account of God; as its ſaid, <hi>he that receiveth you receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me.</hi> Secondly, They ought both to preach, and be received: as they are Miniſters of God, and righteous Men: becauſe the Scriptures, and the ſpirit of truth enjoynes to it; and that's up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of their uprightneſs; both to God and Man, as they are Gods true and faithfull Miniſters. Firſt, Becauſe the true Miniſters of Chriſt <hi>wrongeth no Man.</hi> Secondly, Becauſe they <hi>corrupt no Man.</hi> And thirdly, Becauſe they <hi>defraud no Man,</hi> as you may read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. Theſe therefore who pretend to be Miniſters of God; and are wrongers of Men: and corrupt, and defraud them; are not to be received as the Miniſters of Chriſt: becauſe they are not owned of God: but teſtified againſt by the Scriptures; and alſo by the ſpirit of Chriſt, in the true Goſpell Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The true Goſpell Miniſters, do not ſeek to force in themſelves upon the people; but ſaith <hi>receive us; we have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no man, we have corrupted no man, we have defrauded no man,</hi> as by the Scriptures is evident and plain, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. <note place="margin">Mat. 7.15,16,20,21,22,23. 2 Joh. 7,8,9,10,11.</note> But the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Antichriſt, cannot truly ſay ſo: becauſe by their fruites the contrary is manifeſt: therefore ſuch ought not to be received: but rather rejected; being teſtified againſt by the Scriptures; and alſo by the ſpirit of Chriſt, in the true Goſpel Miniſters, becauſe they are not the Miniſters of Chriſt: but of Antichriſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deceivers and wrongers of God and man, as is evident and plain: 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> &amp; 2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.1,2. 1 Pet. 1.12. Act. 10.42,43. Act. 4 17,18,19,20.</note> Thoſe who are ordained and commanded by the great God of Heaven, to preach the Goſpel unto the ſoules of the people, with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, if Men ſhould forbid them to preach, when God requires them to preach it is better in ſuch a caſe to obey God rather then man: for it was the duty and practice of the Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, when they were forbiden (by men in Authority) to preach any more in the name of Jeſus: to diſobey ſuch commands or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94771:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of men, who forbad them to preach by preaching obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the command and authority of God, who requires it of them; as you may read in the caſe of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the duty and practice of the Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt; in preaching the word, to be inſtant both in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, according to the charge given before the Lord: 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Miniſters of Chriſt ought not to be prohibited, from preaching the Word of God; becauſe by their preaching, they are to be manifeſted to the Conſciences of the people by a Goſpel commendation, that they may be received by them to whoſe conſciences they are commended, in the ſight of God, by manifeſting the truth unto them: but the Miniſters of Antichriſt ought to be rejected (though they pretend to be the Miniſters of Chriſt: becauſe they would come in by force upon the people, to whoſe conſciences they have not commended themſelves (as the Miniſters of God) by manifeſting the truth of the Goſpel unto them, in the ſight of God, as the true Goſpel Miniſters do, and afore-time did.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.21,21. Acts 10.42,43.</note> The Miniſters of Chriſt, ought both to preach, and be received as the Miniſters of God: becauſe they are anointed, and ſealed of God, as well as ordained and ſent, to Miniſter from him to the people for their ſalvation, conſolation and ſoul-ſatisfaction: but the Miniſters of Antichriſt are not to be received: but reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: though they pretend to be the Miniſters of Chriſt) becauſe they are not ordained and ſent of God: (ſecondly) becauſe they are not anointed and ſealed of God: and (thirdly) becauſe they are not appointed by the Lord, to Miniſter from him to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their ſalvation, conſolation, and ſouls-ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, They who are ordained, anointed and ſealed of God, and ſent forth to Miniſter from him, to the ſoules of the people they ought to preach; becauſe they have the earneſt of the ſpirit; of God given into their hearts, as a teſtimony that they are in Covenant with God, and appointed to preach; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21,22,23. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.42,43.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, they ought to preach the Word of God, becauſe they have not Dominion given them over the faith of their Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but are helpers of their joy; for it is by faith that they ſtand; as you may read, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.24.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94771:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
8ly. They ought to Preach, becauſe there is no falſhood in their Doctrine, but as God is true ſo is their Doctrine; for it is not yea and nay, as it is written, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.18,19,21,22,23. but the Miniſters of Antichriſt are not ordained, anointed and ſealed of God, or ſent forth to miniſter from him to the Souls of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for their Salvation, conſolation, or ſouls ſatisfattion; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not to be received as the Miniſters of Chriſt, but rejected as the Miniſters of Antichriſt; 1. Becauſe they have not the earneſt of the Spirit of God given unto them, neither are they guided thereby, but do daily err and go aſtray from Gods own ways; 2. Becauſe they do not help the joy of Believers, but rather fills, them with ſorrow and ſadneſs by ſeeking to have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over their faith, in ſeeking to force in themſelves and their Doctrine and maintenance upon the People, contrary to faith and a good Conſcience whileſt they themſelves are miſerable ſiners, and daily offend againſt Gods holy Laws; 3. They are ſubject to error both in matter and manner, who have no ſaving health in them, whoſe word and doctrine is not true, but yea and nay (according to the times) and contrary to the doctrine of the true Goſpel Miniſters of Chriſt, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>They who are ordained, anointed, and ſealed of God, and ſent to Miniſter from him to the ſoules of the people, <note place="margin">Rom. 8.14,15,16,17.</note> they have the ſpirit of God given unto them to guide them in their miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15,16,17. and if any pretend to be a Miniſter, and have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is no Miniſter of his, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <p>They who have received a Miniſtry from God, they have alſo received a ſpirit ſuitable to ſuch a Miniſtry; that is to ſay the ſpirit of God, whereby they know the things that are freely given unto them; as it is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11,12. for <hi>what Man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the things of a Man, ſave the ſpirit of Man that is in him:</hi> even ſo <hi>the things of God knoweth no Man, but the ſpirit of God. Now we have received the ſpirit of God, that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God,</hi> (ſaid the true Goſpel Miniſters) <hi>which things we alſo ſpeak, not in the words which Mans wiſedome teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but which the holy Ghoſt teacheth,</hi> as yon may read the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11,12. The holy Ghoſt hath a teaching office, in and by the true Goſpel Miniſters; therefore they ought to preach, and none are ſit to be Miniſters, before they receive the holy Ghoſt from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: for men are ignorant of the things of God untill then,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94771:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(Firſt) becauſe no man knowes the things of God, but by the ſpirit of God; ſo that the fpirit of God gives men the knowledg of the things of God in order to adminiſtration; (Secondly) the ſpirit of God is given of God, and received by them that are to miniſter from him, to the ſoules of the people; before they be ſent forth as his Miniſters, and they that receive not the ſpirit of God, receive not a Miniſtry from him, therefore they who have hot the ſpirit of Chriſt, are none of his Miniſters, as it is plain and clear by the Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note>As it is the love of God to give his ſpirit, ſo it is the duty of them to whom it is offered to imbrace and kindly receive ſuch a gift; for they who receive not the ſpirit of God, without which they cannot know the things of God, they are very unfit to be the Miniſters of God, (Firſt) becauſe the ſpirit of God gives men the knowledge of the things of God: (Secondly) becauſe the ſpirit of God; both guides and inables the true Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to preach, or ſpeak the things that are given of God: And (Thirdly) the ſpirit of God guides and inables the true Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Miniſters to preach according to the mind of God; becauſe it teacheth and enableth them to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, in the words which the holy Ghoſt teacheth, and not in the words which mans wiſedome teacheth: the words which mans wiſdome teacheth are not to be uſed in preaching the Goſpel, but that which the holy Ghoſt teacheth: for the Goſpel cannot be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the wiſedome of man, without the holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven; therefore no man can be a true Goſpel Miniſter, but ſuch as have received, and do receive a true Goſpel Spirit to Miniſter withall; as by the Scripture is evident and plain, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11,12,13. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10,11,12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.11,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.13. 1 Pet. 1.10,11,12. Rom. 8.9.</note>The Scripture doth not enable men to be Preachers of Chriſt and the Goſpel without the true Goſpel Spirit, which is the holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven into the hearts of men, for if the Scriptures without the Spirit were ſufficient to enable men, by their own wiſedome to preach the Goſpel, why ſhould the holy Ghoſt be ſent down from Heaven for men to preach the Goſpell by; without which it cannot be done, as by the Scriptures afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid is plain. Knowing this firſt, that no propheſie of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is of any private interpretation; therefore the Scriptures are not to be interpreted in the words which mans wiſedome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94771:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
teacheth: but in the words which the holy Ghoſt teacheth; ſo that man by his wiſedome is no true Interpreter of Scriptures: therefore the right of interpreting Scriptures belongs not to men, by vertue of their humane learning, that ſpeaks and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es the words of mans wiſedome; but the true right of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting Scriptures belongs to them that have received Gods holy Spirit, to give them the knowledge of them, and be a guide un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, both in the adminiſtration and interpretation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for the Propheſie came not in old time by the will of man; <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.20,21.</note> therefore man by his will cannot interpret the Scriptures, but Holy Men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt; ſo that the Holy Ghoſt in them was the moving cauſe of their ſpeaking forth Scriptures, and without the Holy Ghoſt Scriptures cannot be rightly known and interpreted by Men, for the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God, and God hath given his Spirit, and alſo revealed deep things to his Miniſters by his own Spirit; for as no man can know the things of God but by the Spirit of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9,10,11,12,13. ſo the Scriptues being of the things of God no man without the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit can truly know them according to the mind of God, therefore the right of interpreting Scriptures belongs unto men by vertue of the ſpirit of God, from whence Scripture prophecies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20,21. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10,11,12.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.10,11. 1 Pet. 1.10,11,12.</note> No man is to miniſter from God to the Souls of the People, but them to whom the gift of Miniſtration is given, and all men have a true right from God to miniſter from him to the People, unto whom the gift of Miniſtration is given, who are to preach the Goſpel with the holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven for the Peoples Salvation; of which Salvation the Prophets have inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſearched diligently, who propheſied of the grace that ſhould come unto you, ſearching what or what manner of time the Spirit of Chriſt which was in them did ſignifie, when it teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before hand the ſuffering of Chriſt, and the Glory that ſhould follow, unto whom it was revealed that not unto themſelves but unto us they did miniſter the things which are now reported unto you by them that have preached the Goſpel unto you , with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, as every man hath received the gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one unto another as good Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the manifold Grace of God. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10,11, whereby
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94771:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it is evident that Preaching is not an art, but a gift; and they have a true right to be Preachers unto whom the gift of Miniſtration for that end is given, by the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt unto whom the gift of Miniſtratio is given, who are to preach the Goſpel with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, they ought not to be forbidden by Men, nor puniſhed for Preaching the Goſpel: And what Law doth prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit the preaching of Gods Word and the Scriptures, or what is agreeable to the ſame? if any Law ſhould do ſo, would it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contradict the Liturgy of the Church, and the Lawes and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of <hi>England?</hi> becauſe both the Liturgy of the Church, and the Laws and Statutes of <hi>England</hi> allowes of Preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt (the power of God unto Salvation) the pure Word of God, and the Holy Scriptures, and what is either agreeable to the ſame, or evidently grounded thereupon: Then to preach the Goſpel, the pure Word of God, and the Holy Scriptures, or what is agreeable to the ſame, is no matter of fact, becauſe it is not to preach contrary to the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>What the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> allowes of, that the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdom allowes of, but the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> allowes of Chriſtian Religions Meetings, in greater or leſſer numbers for the ſervice and Worſhip of God, according to the Scriptures; and of Preaching the Goſpel, to render thanks unto God (in Godly Aſſemblies, or Chriſtian Religious Meetings) for the great Benefits that we have received at the hands of God, to ſet forth his moſt worthy praiſe, to hear his moſt holy Word, and to ask thoſe things which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and neceſſary both for Soul and Body; being the chiefe ends of Chriſtian Religious Meetings, as the Liturgy alloweth; therefore the Scriptures and Lawes of the Kingdom alloweth of the ſame; what the Scriptures doth allow of, that the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> alloweth of; but the Scripture doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of gifted men to preach the Goſpel with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven; therefore, the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> alloweth of the ſame, for it is declared and ſaid in the Liturgy, <hi>that nothing is ordained to be read</hi> (or obſerved) <hi>but the very pure Word of God, the holy Scriptures, or that which is either agreeable to the ſame or evidently grounded thereupon:</hi> See, that call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſervice of the Church.<note place="margin">See the Order for Morning P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayer. See St. <hi>Peters</hi> day Collect. 1. Pet. 4.10,11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94771:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
To Preach contrary to the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdom is (it ſeems) matter of fact puniſhable by the late Act, but to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, or the very pure Word of God and the holy Scriptures; or what is agreeable to the ſame or evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded thereupon is not (it ſeemes) to preach contrary to the Liturgy and Lawes of the Kingdom, therefore it is no matter of fact nor puniſhable by the late Act for godly Miniſters who are rightly ordained to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, and the very pure Word of God (not being contrary to the Lawes and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Kingdom) becauſe both the Liturgy of the Church, and the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdom allowes of the ſame, as the right matter of Preaching.</p>
            <p>And as for the manner or places for godly Miniſters to pray or preach in, the Lord hath not limited or bound them up to Pariſh Churches and Chappels to aſſemble together to preach and pray in, or elſe be forbidden and caſt out, by the great God of Heaven for refuſing the ſame; for though <hi>Solomon</hi> built him an Houſe, how be it the moſt High dwelleth not now in Temples made with hands, as ſaith (the Lord) the Prophet, <note place="margin">Acts 7.47,48,49,50.</note> 
               <hi>Heaven is my throne, and Earth is my footſtool, what houſe will you build me ſaith the Lord, or where is the place of my reſt? hath not mine hands made all theſe things? Acts</hi> 7.47,48,49,50. Is it not therefore plain by the Scriptures, or may we not learn from hence that the Lord hath <hi>not</hi> limited or bound up his Preachers and People to Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Chappels, or any particular houſe for his Service to be performed in under the Goſpel diſpenſation ſince Chriſts death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, but rather left them to their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom concerning that thing, who hath owned and juſtified his Preachers and People in forſaking the outward Temple at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 7.48,49. Act. 17.24,25.</note> in ſending his Miniſters to preach it down, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.48,49. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24,25. and hath highly owned his. People in Meeting and Preaching in upper Chambers and private Houſes, wherein they have met and aſſembled together (ſince Chriſts Aſcenſion) for the Service and Worſhip of God; but he hath not bound them up or limited them to any one place, as the appointed place of his Worſhip, under the Goſpel diſpenſation ſince Chriſts Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, that in the Scriptures or Writings of the Apoſtles we can any where read of, ſince he ſent them to preach down the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94771:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſaith, nothing is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to be read or obſerved amongſt Chriſtians about the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Church; but <hi>the very pure word of God, the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or that which is either agreeable to the ſame, or evidently ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereupon, and that Chriſts Goſpell is not a Ceremoniall Law,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Service of the Church, and that of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and the Epiſtle &amp; collect for the 2d. Sunday in Advent.</note> (as much of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law was) but it is a Religion to ſerve God, not in bondage of the figure or ſhaddow, but in freedome of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and likewiſe it is ſaid both in the Scriptures and Liturgy of the Church; that <hi>whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our Learning;</hi> whereby it is evident that whatſoever is agreeable to the holy Scriptures and pure Word of God, is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to be read or obſerved in Chriſtian Aſſemblies and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practices. 2ly. That Chriſtians are not to be bound up and tyed to the obſervation of the Figure, ſhadow or ceremonies, or brought in bondage of the figure or ſhadow of things, about the ſervice of God. 3ly. That Chriſtians are to ſtand faſt in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty wherewith Chriſt hath ſet them free, and not to be intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with figures, ſhadowes or ceremonies, which may hinder them from the Service of God, which ſtands in the freedom of the Spirit. 4ly. That the holy Scriptures which were written afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, are to be obſerved by Chriſtians, becauſe they were written for our inſtruction or learning, as both the Liturgy and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are evident and plain.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing it is ſo, we find it written in the holy Scriptures, and left upon record there for our inſtruction or learning, about the true Ordination of Goſpel Miniſters, or their call to the work of the Miniſtry ſince Chriſts Aſcenſion: <note place="margin">Acts 13.</note> Firſt, That the Holy Ghoſt is of Councel with the true Church, and hath a ruling po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer therein, for ordering and governing the ſame, and that the Liturgy agreeth with, becauſe it ſaith, <hi>the Church is the houſhold and family of God, and that the whole body of the Church is governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Good Friday the Collect.</note> whereby it appears that the true Church is a ſanctified body, and under a Spiritual order and Government, and that Church and Miniſtry which hath Chriſts ſpiritual Preſence with them, is the true Church and Miniſtry of Chriſt, <note place="margin">Matt. 28.18,19,20.</note> becauſe he hath promiſed to be alwaies with them, <hi>even to the end of the world;</hi> as by the Spirit that is of Councel with the Church and the holy Scriptures, we are inſtructed and have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them the knowledg thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94771:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Secondly, We are inſtructed and have learned, by the ſpirit from whence the holy Scriptures proceeded, and by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which aforetime were written and proceeded therefrom: that as the holy Ghoſt is of councel with the true Church, ſo the true Church doth take councel of the holy Ghoſt, and is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and ſubject to the holy Ghoſts order, authority and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment: <note place="margin">Acts 13.1,2,3,4.</note> now there were in the Church that was at <hi>Antioch</hi> certain Prophets and Teachers, as <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Simeon</hi> that was called <hi>Niger,</hi> and <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> and <hi>Manaen</hi> which had been brought up with <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Tetrarch,</hi> and <hi>Saul:</hi> as they miniſtred to the Lord and faſted, the holy Ghoſt ſaid, <hi>Separate me</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Saul, <hi>for the mork whereunto I have called them,</hi> and when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away; ſo they being ſent forth by the holy Ghoſt, departed unto <hi>Seleucia,</hi> and from thence they ſailed to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and left upon record in Scripture: <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1,2,3,4.</p>
            <p>Whereby we are inſtructed, or from whence we do obſerve and may learn; that in the true Church of Chriſt (which was at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi>) there were certain Prophets and Teachers, which were not Pariſh Prieſts, or bound up and tyed to one particular Pariſh, to ſtay and continue there, preaching for <hi>Tithes, Eaſter reckonings,</hi> and <hi>Midſumer dues;</hi> all the dayes of their lives. Secondly, That thoſe Prophets and Teachers which were in the true Church, of which Chriſt Jeſus is head; they attended upon the work of the Lord, and both faſted and miniſtred unto him, (and did not ſue people for Tithes, nor caſt them into Priſon; for we do not learn by the Scriptures, that true Goſpel Preachers were ever found in any ſuch actions) Thirdly, That as they miniſtred to the Lord and faſted, the holy Ghoſt manifeſted his mind to the Church, being of counſel with the ſame, requiring obedience of the Church, as a manifeſtation of their ſubjection to the holy Ghoſts Order and Authority; who manifeſted the right that he had in the true and right Ordination of Miniſters, or calling of them to the work of the Miniſtry, and ſending them abroad to preach the Goſpel; for the holy Ghoſt ſaid to the Church, <hi>Separate me</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas <hi>and</hi> Saul <hi>for the work whereunto I have called them:</hi> from whence we are inſtructed, and do obſerve or learn, (Firſt) That the holy Ghoſt hath a true Right and Authority to Ordain Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, or call them to the work of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94771:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Miniſtry, and ſend them to Preach: (Secondly) That theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters who are called by the holy Ghoſt, to the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and ſent forth to preach; as ſuch were; they are rightly and truly ordained and ſent forth to preach, and ought neither to be forbiden to preach the pure word of God, nor puniſhed for ſo doing; becauſe we find in the Scripture, which the <hi>Liturgie</hi> ſaith, was written aforetime for our learning, that ſuch as have the word of God to ſpeak; ought not to be forbiden to preach it: for as much as the Lord commands them to ſpeak it: <note place="margin">Jer. 23.28,29,30,31,32.</note> 
               <hi>is not my word like a Fire ſaith the Lord, and like a Hammer that breaketh the Rock in pieces: therefore behold I am againſt the Prophets,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>that ſteale my words every one from his neighbour, who uſe their tongues, and ſay he ſaith, whom I never commanded nor ſent ſaith the Lord:</hi> who hath alſo ſaid, that ſuch <hi>falſe Teachers do cauſe the People to erre by their lyes, and by their lightneſs:</hi> and ſuch the Lord is againſt, as you may read, <hi>but he that hath my word, let him ſpeak my word faithfully; what is the Chaff to the Wheat ſaith the Lord: Jer.</hi> 23.28,29,30,31,32. (Thirdly) The holy Ghoſt ſpake to the Church, whereby it is evident that the holy Ghoſt ſpeaks in the true Church, and the Church is acquainted with the holy Ghoſt and his teachings; and therefore ſtands not to diſpute its commands, or diſobey the holy Ghoſts Order and Authority; <note place="margin">Acts 13.</note> but being commanded by the holy Ghoſt to ſeparate <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> for the work of the Miniſtry, whereunto the holy Ghoſt had ordained or called them, the true Church never queſtioned whether ſuch a Call was ſufficient, without a ſignification of the conſent and allowance of <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> in a Nationall way, or as the manner now is amongſt ſuch as may be, will deny the way and manner of the proceedings of the holy Ghoſt in that caſe of calling and ſending forth Miniſters, as aforeſaid, to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt: <note place="margin">Acts 13 1,2,3,4. 1 Tim. 3.1,2,3,4,5,6,7. Tit. 1 7,8,9.</note> but if they do, is it not below a true Goſpel <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſo to do; who ought not to ſhew a diſlike unto, and diſeſteem of, what the holy Ghoſt and the true Church of Chriſt and the Scripture do juſtify and own, concerning the ſame, but I hope it may be well for them who are ſo in account; to take it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to due conſideration, ſo as not to condemn, but rather allow of the holy Ghoſts order and proceedings, and the true Churches example or practiſe therein; ſeeing that what the holy Scripture allowes of: that the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> allowes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94771:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of; and it is evident that the holy Scriptures allowes of the ſame as aforeſaid; for the Holy Ghoſt ſaid to the Church, <hi>ſeparate me</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Saul <hi>for the work whereunto I have called them;</hi> and when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them they ſent them away; ſo they being ſent forth by the Holy Ghoſt departed, and when they were at <hi>Salamis</hi> they preached the Word of God to the People, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1,2,3,4. Whereby it is evident that the Holy Ghoſt hath a true right to call to the work of the Miniſtry of Chriſt, and that they who are called to that work by the Holy Ghoſt, ought not to be forbidden to preach, becauſe they are both truly ordained and ſent, and have the Word of God to preach to the people, being alſo accompanied with a true ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual power and filled with the Holy Ghoſt, that hath called and ſent them to preach as aforeſaid; after they were at <hi>Salamis</hi> and had gone through the Iſland unto <hi>Paphos,</hi> they found a certain <hi>Sorcerer,</hi> a falſe Prophet, a <hi>Jew,</hi> with the <hi>Deputy</hi> of the Country, a prudent Man, who called for <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> and deſired to hear the Word of God; but <hi>Elimus</hi> the Sorcerer withſtood them, ſeeking to turn away the <hi>Deputy</hi> from the faith, (as falſe teachers geting into favour with Governours and Deputy Governours, and great perſons, often times endeavour to do) then <hi>Saul,</hi> who is alſo called <hi>Paul,</hi> who was filled with the Holy Ghoſt (that call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſent him to preach) ſaid unto the falſe Prophet (that ſought to turn away the Deputy Governour from the faith) <hi>Oh full of all ſubtlety and all miſchief, thou child of the Devil, thou enemy of all Righteouſneſs, wilt thou not ceaſe to pervert the right wayes of the Lord, Acts</hi> 13.6,7,8,9,10. Whereby it is evident and plain, that the Holy Ghoſt filleth true Preachers with ſpiritual boldneſs ſharply to reprove and teſtifie againſt a falſe Prophet in the preſence of a Deputy or Governour of a Country.</p>
            <p>They who are ordained and ſent of God, as aforeſaid, ought not to be forbidden to preach, or puniſhed for preaching the word of the Lord to the People, becauſe they preach the Everlaſting Goſpel, and thereby do miniſter the Spirit and power of God to Salvation unto Believers, and ſuch have not dominion over the faith of their hearers but are appointed of God to be helpers of the joy of Believers. 2ly. They ought not to be forbidden to preach the Word of God to the people, becauſe that by vertue of their preaching (the Lord opperating with them in their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94771:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts 26.16,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7,18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m 5.20.</note> they do convert people from the evil of their wayes and doings by turning them from darkneſs unto light, and ſo from the power of Satan unto God; whereby it may be obſerved that to hinder ſuch Miniſters from Preaching, would be to hinder the work of converſion, and ſo to oppoſe the work of the Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. 3ly. They ought not to be hindered from preaching who have the Word of the Lord to ſpeak to the People, and do preach it freely without <hi>Tithes, Eaſier Reckonings</hi> or <hi>Midſummer dews,</hi> who covet no mans Silver nor Gold for their Preaching; <note place="margin">Acts 20.27,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8,29,30,31,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2,33,34,35.</note> becauſe God hath ordained that they who preach the Goſpel ſhould deny Tythes and live of the Goſpel; it is neceſſary therefore firſt to know what the Goſpel is. 2ly. Who have a right to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt unto the people: And 3ly. what it is for true Preachers to live on the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to the firſt as concerning the Goſpel of Chriſt what it is, it is declared in Scripture, <hi>to be the power of God unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to every one that believeth;</hi> wherein the Righteouſneſs of God is revealed from faith to faith, as it is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.15,16,17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6,7,8,9,10,11,12,15,16. 2ly. They have a true right to preach the Goſpel who have rightly received the ſame, ſo that the Goſpel is to be rightly received before it can be rightly preached, and the Goſpel is not to be received of man, how then can men impower to the effectual true and right Preaching of the ſame; for <hi>Paul</hi> (who was a true Goſpel Preacher) was taught of God how to miniſter from him to the People, and received the Goſpel by the Revelation of Chriſt, and not of man, as he hath certified to the Brethren as we ſaid before, ſo ſay I now again, <hi>If any man preach any other Goſpel unto you then that ye have received let him be accurſed, Gal</hi> 1.8,9. and before, that is to ſay in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> he ſaid, <note place="margin">Rom. 1.16. Gal. 1.11,12.</note> 
               <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, for it is the power of God unto Salvation to every one that believeth, Rom.</hi> 1.16. this Goſpel which is the power of God is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of God by them that are true Preachers of the ſame; <hi>but I certifie you brethren that the Goſpel which was preached of me was not after man, for I neither received it of man neither was I taught it, but by Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as it is written, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11,12.</p>
            <p>Whereby it is evident, or from hence we may obſerve and learn, firſt, that the goſpel of Chriſt is the power of God unto Salvation, to every one that believeth, wherein the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94771:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of God is revealed. 2ly. That Revelation is not ceaſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in the Miniſtration of the Goſpel which is the power of God unto Salvation, as aforeſaid, Gods Righteouſneſs is revealed. 3ly. That the Goſpel is to be received, before it can be preached, and it is to be revealed before it can be received or preached. 4ly. That the Goſpel of Chriſt which is the power of God unto Salvation is neither received nor taught after Men, but by Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. 5ly. That they who deny Revelation, they have neither received the Goſpel, which is the power wherein the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God is revealed; nor the Righteouſneſs of God which is revealed in the Goſpel of Chriſt as aforeſaid; for ſaith the Apoſtle who received the Goſpel of Chriſt, <note place="margin">Gal. 1.15,16</note> 
               <hi>I neither received it of man, neither was I taught it, but by Revelation, Gal.</hi> 1.11,12. <hi>And when it pleaſed God, who ſeperated me from my Mothers womb, and called me by his grace to reveal his Son in me, that I might preach Him among the Heathen; immediately I conferred not with fleſh and blood, neither went I up to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to them that were Apoſtles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me; but I went into</hi> Arabia, <hi>&amp;c. Gal.</hi> 1.15,16. whereby it is evident and from hence we may obſerve and learn that the Goſpel is known by Revelation. 2ly. That they who deny Revelation are no true Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt. 3ly. That it is the good pleaſure of God to call ſuch as he makes choice of to ſerve in the work of the Goſpel of Chriſt. 41y. That the call to the Miniſtry is not an act of Nature but of Grace, 5ly. That Chriſt is revealed in a true Goſpel Miniſter before he be at fit Preacher, 6ly.. That after a Miniſter be called by the Grace of God to the work of the Miniſtry, and Chriſt Jeſus revealed ſpiritually in him he is a fit Preacher without going to Men for their Approbation concerning the ſame. Now if either ignorance or wilfulneſs ſhould object and ſay, <note place="margin">Mat. 11.27</note> 
               <hi>that things were made known in the Apoſtles time by Revelation, but it is ceaſed ſince then, and there is no ſuch thing to be expected or looked for now.</hi> I anſwer thereunto, Chriſt Jeſus hath ſaid, <note place="margin">Luk. 10.22</note> 
               <hi>No man knows the Father but the Son, neither knoweth any man the Son but the Father, and he to whom he is pleaſed to reveal him.</hi> Therefore they that ſay Revelation is ceaſed, do in effect ſay that the way and means to attain to the knowledge of God is ceaſed, for no man can come to the knowledg of God but by Revelation, and if Revelation be ceaſed then no man can come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, but remain in ignorance of him, and <hi>periſh for want of knowledg, Hoſea</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94771:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Thirdly, As to that of Preachers who have received the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, it is ordained that they who preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel, and not of Tythes, becauſe they are no Goſpel main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; for they who are ordained of God to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, which is the power of God unto Salvation, they do miniſter the Spirit and Power of God unto Believers: Therefore, they that live of the Goſpel do live of the free gift of the <hi>Power</hi> which opens the hearts of their Hearers freely to communicate to them. Therefore it's ſaid, <hi>let him that is taught in the Word communicate to him that teacheth, in all gord things, Gal.</hi> 6.6. Whereby it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident or from hence we may obſerve and learn, firſt, that people are not injoyned by the Goſpel to communicate any thing to any man as a Preacher, by whom they were never taught in the Word: 2ly. That none ought to communicate any thing upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Preaching but ſuch as are taught in the Word: 3ly. That Believers are not compelled by the Goſpel, nor compellable to communicate to Preachers, but are left to the powerful opperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Word of God, as it may open their hearts and diſpoſe of them in that reſpect: 4ly. That they are not to give place to any thing that would obſtruct the office of love begotten in their hearts, by the preaching of the Word of God unto them, but are to let it ſhew forth its fruit and freeneſs in the act of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating unto them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l. 6.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Concerning Chriſtian Religious Meetings, and preaching in Houſes, &amp;c. Whereas it is declared, <hi>by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> to be an offence againſt Law, and puniſhable with Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment: Fines and Baniſhment, for Perſons to meet together to the number of five or above, beſide them of the Houſhold, under pretence of Religious exerciſe, in other manner then is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Then it is no offence againſt Law nor puniſhable thereby, to meet in greater numbers upon the account of Religion and Worſhip of God; So that the manner of their Meeting be allowed by the <hi>Liturgie.</hi> What is contained in the Liturgy, as to the manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings; is allowed by the <hi>Liturgie;</hi> But the manner of Meeting by Chriſt and his Apoſtles and the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the <hi>Liturgie.</hi> Therefore the manner of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Meetings, in other places then in Pariſh Churches and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94771:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is allowed by the <hi>Liturgie;</hi> ſo that ſuch Meetings ought not to be accounted ſeditious Conventicles, nor puniſhable by Law.</p>
            <p>That which is contained in the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and ordained to be read, as part of the practiſe or ſervice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is owned and allowed by the <hi>Liturgie</hi> and practiſe of the Church. But the manner of the Meetings, Aſſemblies and Preachings, by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to and amongſt the Primitive Chriſtians, and ſuch as came to hear the word of God ſpoken unto them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mountains and by the Sea ſide, and alſo in private Houſes and other places is contained in the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and ordained to be read as part of the practiſe or ſervice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch manner of Meetings, Aſſemblies or Preachings, or the manner of ſuch Chriſtian Religious Meetings, Aſſemblies and practiſes are no ſeditious Conventicles; nor puniſhable by Law; becauſe they are owned and allowedly the Liturgy and practiſe of the Church, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>That the manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings, Aſſemblies and practiſes (in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chapels) is contained in the <hi>Liturgie</hi> and ordained to be read as part of the practiſe or ſervice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and allowed, as aforeſaid is very plain and apparently proved both by the Scripture and Liturgy.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By the Scriptures it is apparent and evident that Chriſt and his Apoſtles, did meet and aſſemble with the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſuch as came to hear the word of God preached, in private Houſes, and upon Mountains, and by the Sea ſide as well as other places; and they left their manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings, Aſſemblies, and practiſes (in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chapels) upon Record in Scripture, as an example for Chriſtians to follow. Becauſe the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who had the ſpirit and mind of Chriſt Jeſus, commands the true Chriſtians and Believers in Chriſt to <hi>walk as they have them for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> as by the Scripture is plainly apparent: <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. For Chriſt and his Apoſtles met and aſſembled together with the Primitive Chriſtians and others, and preached in Houſes and out of houſes, on Mountains, and by the Sea ſide; and in great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes: as you may read, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.1,2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.1,2,3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.3,4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And again he entred into <hi>Capernaum</hi> after ſome dayes, and it was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94771:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
noiſed that he was in the Houſe, and ſtreight way many were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, in ſo much that there was no room to receive them, not ſo much as about the Door, and he preached the word unto them, as you may read, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.1,2. and he began to teach by the Sea ſide, and there was gathered unto him a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and he taught them there alſo, as you may read, <hi>Mark</hi> 4. ſee alſo <hi>Mark</hi> 10.1. and he came down with them and ſtood in the plain, and the company of his Diſciples, and a great multitude of people, out of all <hi>Judea,</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and from the Coaſt of <hi>Tire</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> came to hear him, as it is written, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.17. and he aroſe from thence, and cometh into the Coaſts of <hi>Judea,</hi> by the farther fide of <hi>Jordan;</hi> and the people reſorted to him again, and as he was wont, he taught them again, <hi>Mark</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And when much people were gathered together and were come to him out of every City, he preached unto them, and he went thorough every City and Village preaching, and ſhewing the glad tidings of the Kingdome of God, and the twelve were with him, as you may read, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.1,4. Whereby it is evident, that Chriſt did not limit the people, to come to Pariſh Churches, to hear the Word preached, nor the Miniſters of the Goſpel to preach it there; neither did he ordain puniſhments for the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or hearers; if they did not preach and hear in Pariſh Churches and not elſe where, but to the number of three or four: for when they were gathered together, an innumerable multitude of people, in ſo much that they erode one upon another; he began to ſay unto his Diſciples, firſt of all, beware ye of the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypocriſy, for there is nothing covered that ſhall not be revealed, neither hid that ſhall not be known, as you may read, <hi>Luke</hi> 12, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. <hi>Luke,</hi> 8.1: And after Chriſts Death, Reſurrection and Aſcention, the Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians, did Aſſemble and meet together, to preach and pray, and performe religions exerciſe, to the number of five and above; and not in Pariſh Churches nor Chapels: but in private houſes and uper chambers, and ſuch like places; and ſuch godly Meetings were no ſeditious Conventicles, but according to the example and practiſe ordained of Chriſt Jeſus: for he ſhewed himſelf alive after his paſſion unto them by many infallible proof: being ſeen of them forty dayes, and ſpeaking of the things par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Kingdome of God; as you may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1,2,3.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94771:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and being aſſembled with them, (after his Reſurrection, when he was ready to aſcend up into Heaven) he commanded them that they ſhould not depart from <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but wait for (the holy Ghoſt from Heaven) the promiſe of the Father, which ſaith he, ye have heard of me: and they returned to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that command, from the Mount called <hi>Olivet,</hi> after Chriſt was aſcended; but they did not go into (a Pariſh Church or a Chappel, nor into) the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to wait for the promiſe of the Father: Therefore Chriſt did not command them to go into a Pariſh Church or Chappel, nor into the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to wait upon God to receive the promiſe, for if he had, no doubt but they would have obeyed his command, in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>They were commanded to wait at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for the promiſe of the Father, and they did ſo in obedience to the command of Chriſt Jeſus: but they were not commanded by Chriſt to wait in the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> nor in a Pariſh Church; for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the promiſe of the Father, (or the holy Ghoſt) but rather in a private Houſe: Therefore neither the Temple at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> nor a Pariſh Church, was the place appointed for them to meet in, to wait for the promiſe of the Father; but rather an uper Chamber, or a private Houſe. Then returned they unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from the Mount called <hi>Olivet;</hi> and when they were come in, they went up into an uper Room, where abode both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Andrew: Phillip</hi> and <hi>Thomas, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi> and <hi>Matthew, James</hi> the Son of <hi>Alpheus,</hi> and <hi>Simon Zelotes,</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> the brother of <hi>James,</hi> theſe (were met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to perform ſervice to God, for they) continued with one accord in prayer and ſupplication, with the Women, and <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and with his brethren, and there were met and aſſembled together, upon the account of the exerciſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to the number of five and above, beſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them of the Houſhold, in that upper Chamber where they were together, for) in thoſe dayes <hi>Peter</hi> ſtood up in the midſt of the Diſciples and ſpoak, (the number of Names together were about one hundred and twenty) and when the day of <hi>Pentecoaſt</hi> was fully come; they were all with one accord in one place, (and the place where they were when they received the holy Ghoſt; was neither a Pariſh Church nor a Chapel, but a private Houſe) and ſuddenly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94771:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there came a ſound from Heaven as of a ruſhing mighty Wind, and it filled all the Houſe where they were ſiting, (and there they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the promiſe of the Father) for they were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt, as both by the Scriptures and <hi>Liturgie</hi> is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and evident; ſee for proof thereof, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. and <hi>Acts</hi> 2. And to prove that the Liturgy alloweth of Meeting in upper Rooms, and private Houſes, for the exerciſe of Religion as aforeſaid; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it alloweth of ſuch godly Aſſemblies and Meetings, (though not in Pariſh Churches or Chappels) as were practiced by the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and Primitive Chriſtians as aforeſaid; for proof thereof, ſee in the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> the <hi>Epiſtle for Whitſunday,</hi> and <hi>for St. Mathias, day the Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Liturgie</hi> alſo alloweth of the manner of Meetings and Preaching both in great numbers and multitudes, and in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels, becauſe it alloweth of the manner of Meetings and Preaching by Chriſt and his Apoſtles amongſt the Primitive Chriſtians and others.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Liturgie</hi> ſaith, <hi>it came to paſs that as the People preſſed upon him</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>to hear the Word of God, he ſtood by the Lake of</hi> Geneſareth <hi>and ſaw two Ships ſtanding by the Lake, and he entered into one of the Ships which was</hi> Simons, <hi>and he ſate down and taught the People out of the Ship.</hi> See the 5<hi>th. Sunday after Trinity, the Goſpel.</hi> Whereby it appears that the <hi>Liturgie</hi> alloweth of the manner of meeting and preaching in a Ship, and by the Sea ſide, as aforeſaid. Therefore the Liturgy alloweth of the manner of Meeting and Preaching in other places beſides Pariſh Churches and Chappels.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Great multitudes followed Chriſt, as by the <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> appeareth; See the 8<hi>th. Sunday after Trinity the Goſpel,</hi> and he preached unto them, then drew near unto him all the Publicanes and Sinners for to hear him, (when he was in a Phariſees Houſe) and the Scribes and Phariſees murmured at him, ſaying, <hi>this man receiveth ſinners and eateth with them:</hi> then <hi>Jeſus</hi> began to ſpeak to them by a Parable, as you may read, ſee the <hi>third Sunday after Trinity, the Goſpel;</hi> ſee alſo <hi>Luke the</hi> 14. and <hi>Luke</hi> 15. <hi>Chap.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeareth that Chriſt was ready to do good unto Sinners? and refuſed not to preach unto them (though he was not in a Pariſh Church) but in a Phariſees Houſe as aforeſaid. The <hi>Liturgie</hi> faith, <hi>Peter opened his mouth and ſaid, of a truth I perceive that God is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94771:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
no reſpecter of perſons, but in every Nation he that feareth God and worketh Righteouſneſs is accepted with him.</hi> And where was <hi>Peter</hi> when he preached this Doctrine but in the Houſe of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and not in a Pariſh Church or Chappel, whereby it is evident that the Scriptures and Liturgy allowes of both Meeting and Preaching in private Houſe as aforeſaid; ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 10. and <hi>Eaſter Munday the Epiſtle,</hi> for proof of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Again the <hi>Liturgie</hi> ſaith, Chriſt preached on a Mountain, and in great multitudes alſo; ſee <hi>All-Saints</hi> day.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All Saints day the Goſpel, &amp; Whitſunday the Epiſtle.</note>Again for meeting in private Houſes upon the account of the exerciſe of Religion, the <hi>Liturgie</hi> ſaith, that <hi>when the day of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt was fully come, they were all with one accord in one place, and ſuddenly there came a ſound from Heaven, as of a mighty ruſhing wind, and it filled the houſe where they were ſiting, and they were all filled with the holy Ghoſt and began to ſpeak as the Spirit gave them utterance.</hi> Whereby it is evident and apparent, firſt, That it was the practice of the Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians to meet in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Houſe to wait upon the Lord. 2ly. That God owned and honoured ſuch Chriſtian Religious meetings, though they were (not in Pariſh Churches or Chappels) but in private Houſes, and that by ſending the Holy Ghoſt from Heaven to them, as aforeſaid. 3ly. That the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Liturgie</hi> alloweth and owneth the manner of ſuch Chriſtian and religious Meetings and practices, though not in Pariſh Churches or Chappels, but in a Houſes as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid. Likewiſe the <hi>Liturgie</hi> ſaith, <hi>That in thoſe days Peter ſtood up in the midſt of the Diſciples, and ſaid,</hi> (the number of them by name being about one hundred and twenty) <hi>Men and Brethren this Scripture muſt needs be fulfilled which the Holy Ghoſt ſpake by the mouth of David.</hi> And where was <hi>Peter</hi> (and about one hundred and twenty more) when he ſaid ſo unto them? were they not met together in an upper Chamber; ſee the <hi>Liturgie St. Mathias, for the Epiſtle,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 1.12,13,14,15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is it not therefore according both to the manner allowed by the Scripture and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy for Chriſtians to meet and aſſemble together upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion to the number of five and above over and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides them of the houſhold or family, where they do meet and aſſemble together, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Many more examples of the manner of Chriſtian religious Meetings might be inſtanced out of the Liturgy, but I ſhall only
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94771:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
mention one other inſtance out of the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> which I judge may be ſufficient as to that matter, with a few more Scripture examples concerning the manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings and practices to prove the lawfulneſs of them: That which the <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> declares to be very meet and right to be done muſt needs be allowed by the ſame, but the <hi>Liturgie</hi> declares it to be very meet and right for Chriſtians to meet together at all times and in all places for the Service of God; therefore the <hi>Liturgie</hi> alloweth of the manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings at any time and in any place for the ſervice of God as aforeſaid; that which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the <hi>Liturgie</hi> to be the duty of Chriſtians muſt needs be allowed by the <hi>Liturgie;</hi> but it is declared by the <hi>Liturgie</hi> to be the duty <hi>of Chriſtians at all times and in all places to give thanks, or perform ſervice to the Almighty God:</hi> therefore the <hi>Liturgie</hi> muſt needs allow of the ſame, at any time and in any place to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and done, it is very meet, right, and our bounden duty that we ſhould at all times and in all places perform ſervice unto the Lord; for proof whereof, ſee the <hi>Liturgie</hi> in that part called <hi>the Communion.</hi> Seeing that the Liturgy alloweth of the manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings for the ſervice of God at all times and in all places, it allowes of Meetings in private Houſes, and in upper Chambers and other places, as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> do, or elſe the <hi>Liturgie</hi> would contradict and oppoſe the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and practices of the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians; but they who have a reverend eſteem of the <hi>Liturgie</hi> muſt needs ſay that what the holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> allowes of, that the <hi>Liturgie</hi> allowes of, and as the holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> allowes of the manner of Chriſtian Religious Meetings, Preachings and practices (in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels) ſo the <hi>Liturgie</hi> (that it may be juſtified by the holy Scriptures concerning the manner of ſuch Chriſtian Religious meetings and practices) alloweth of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians did meet together to preach and pray, and perform duty and ſervice to God, and the manner of their Meetings were in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels, and ſuch meetings were no ſeditious Conventicles but lawful Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, They did meet and aſſemble together for the ſervice and Worſhip of God after Chriſts Aſcenſion in private Houſes and upper Chambers, as you may read, <hi>Acts,</hi> 1.13,14,15. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1,2.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:94771:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Thirdly, <hi>And when they had prayed the place was ſhaken where they were aſſembled together, and they were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt, and they ſpake the word of God with boldneſs, Acts</hi> 4.31,32.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They were lawfull Meetings, though in private Houſes, and owned by the Lord: becauſe he filled them with the holy Ghoſt, to ſpeak the word of God with boldneſs; whereby it is evident that godly Miniſters are juſtified by the Lord, and may preach the word of God boldly, in uper Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and private Houſes, as you may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. That the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> preached in a Chamber on the firſt day of the Week until midnight, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7,8. And <hi>Peter</hi> preached boldly and effectually in the Houſe of <hi>Cornelius; Acts</hi> 10: and <hi>Paul</hi> preached two yeares, in his own hired Houſe, and received all that came unto him: preaching the Kingdome of God, and teaching thoſe things which concerned the Lord Jeſus Chriſt with all confidence, no man forbiding him, as it is written, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.30,31. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is evident that God owns and juſtifies Meetings and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Houſes, and that a Miniſter of Chriſt, may preach in other places beſides Pariſh Churches and Chapels, and in his own hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Houſe alſo, and there receive ſuch as come to be inſtructed by him, in the matters of the Kingdome of God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is evident and plain therefore by the holy Scripture, and alſo by the <hi>Liturgie</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and meeting in Houſes is owned and honoured by the Lord, and ought not to be condemned, but juſtified by the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and believers in Chriſt; for to condemn the Miniſters of Chriſt, and true Chriſtians for preaching and meeting in Houſes upon the account of Religion and worſhip of God, would be to condemn the practiſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians recorded in Scriptures; and it would be to deny and diſallow of what God Almighty and the holy Scriptures do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently juſtify and own, and therefore meeting and preaching in Houſes ought not to be forbiden or puniſhed by men; becauſe ſuch Chriſtian Religious Meetings, preaching and practiſes are allowed by the Liturgy, and owned, and honoured by the Lord God of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That which is allowed by the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and owned, and honoured by the Lord God of Heaven, ought not to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94771:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and condemned by men, but Chriſtian Religious Meetings and preaching, in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chapels are allowed by the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and owned and honoured by the Lord God of Heaven: Therefore Chriſtian Religious Meetings and preachings in Houſes, or in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chapels, as aforeſaid, ought not to be forbiden, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by men.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians did frequently meet together after Chriſts Aſcenſion, in Houſes to preach and pray and perform ſervice to God, and that ſuch Chriſtian Religious meetings and preaching in Houſes were own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and honoured by the Lord God of Heaven, is plain and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved as aforeſaid, and therefore ſuch Chriſtian religious meetings and preachings are allowed by the Lord to be lawful aſſemblies and practiſes; which ought to be allowed and tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by men; becauſe they are owned and juſtified by the great God of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians to whom Chriſt appeared after his Reſurrection, and gave command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to wait at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> untill they received the promiſe of the Father, or the Holy Ghoſt from Heaven, did in obedience to that Command return from the Mount <hi>Olivet</hi> after Chriſts Aſcenſion unto <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to wait for the Holy Ghoſt from Heaven, but they did not go into the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> nor into a Pariſh Church or Chappel to wait for the ſame, but they entered into <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and went into an upper Room and was ſitting together in a Houſe when they received the Holy Ghoſt from Heaven, as by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are evident and plain, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. and <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, or from hence we may obſerve and learn, firſt, That the Pariſh Churches and Chappels were not the places appointed by Chriſt at his Aſcenſion to meet and aſſemble together in, to wait upon God untill they received the Holy Ghoſt from Heaven. 2ly. That God is not bound or tyed up to Pariſh Churches or Chappels to wait upon him therein, as the appointed place of his Worſhip. 3ly. That the Lord God Almighty hath ſignally own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and teſtified from Heaven that he owns and juſtifies meetings in Houſes to wait upon him, beauſe when they were met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94771:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as they ſate in a Houſe they received the Holy Ghoſt from Heaven, and ſpake as the Spirit gave them utterance; but we do not read in the Scriptures that Almighty God did ever at any time ſo wonderfully manifeſt himſelf to People in a Pariſh Church or Chappel, as in Houſes he hath done, ſince Chriſts Aſcenſion into Heaven.</p>
            <p>Fifthly. The Lord hath ſo far owned and honoured Meeting and Preaching in Houſe ſince Chriſts Aſcenſion that the Hearers have received the Holy Ghoſt, at meeting and preaching in Houſes as by the Scripture is evident and plain; therefore meeting and preaching in Houſes ought not to be forbidden; but when did the Lord ſo evidently appear and ſignally own meeting and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in Pariſh Churches and Chappels as then and therein to give the Holy Ghoſt to the Hearers, as at preaching in Houſes he hath done; for when <hi>Peter</hi> was preaching in the houſes of <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Holy Ghoſt fell on al them which heard the word, as you may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. from <hi>verſe</hi> 19. to <hi>verſe</hi> 49. whereby it appears that meeting and preaching in houſes are owned and honoured of God, as by the Scriptures is apparently proved.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>And when the day of Pentecoſt was fully come, they were all with one accord in one place, and ſuddenly there came a ſound from Heaven and filled all the Houſe where they were ſitting;</hi> whereby it appeares, that they were aſſembled and met in a Houſe, and that Chriſtian meeting was no ſeditious Conventicle; but owned and honoured by the Lord from Heaven; though they were not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in a Pariſh Church or Chapel, but in a Houſe, whereby it appeares that God is well pleaſed with meeting and preaching in Houſes; <hi>for they were filled with the holy Ghoſt, and ſpake, as the ſpirit gave them utterance,</hi> though ſome mocking of them, ſaid <hi>theſe men are full of new Wine,</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> ſtanding up, with the Elders, lift up his voice and preached unto them, and <hi>when they had heard him preach the word of God unto them, they were pricked in their hearts;</hi> and <hi>the ſame day there were added unto them about three thouſand ſoules, and they continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles doctrine and fellowſhip;</hi> as you may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1,2. to the 43. Whereby it appears that the Word of God may be effectually preached in houſes; was there ever ſuch a thing known at a meeting in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church or Chappel, by the preaching of a Pariſh Prieſt in thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94771:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
places to convert at one Sermon three thouſand Souls, as was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually done by the preaching of the Word by the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> as aforeſaid; therefore it is apparent arid evident by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that meeting and preaching in houſes are lawful meetings and practices, being ſo highly approv'd of, and ſignally owned of the Lord, and ſuch meetings and preaching in Houſes as are own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and approved of God ought not to be forbidden by men, but rather allowed and tollerated by them.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Though God Almighty did ſo evidently ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf well pleaſed with meeting and preaching in Houſes in the Primitive times as aforeſaid, yet the unbelievers and formal envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Profeſſors who were out of love with the ſame, and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which God did ſo ſignally own by apparent Teſtimonies from Heaven, for <hi>the Jewes which believe not, moved with envy took unto them certain leud fellowes of the baſer ſort, and gathered a company and ſet all the City in an uproar, and aſſaulted the houſe of</hi> Jaſon, <hi>and ſought to bring them out to the people, and they drew</hi> Jaſon <hi>and certain Brethren unto the Rulers of the City, crying, theſe that have turend the World upſide down are come hither alſo, whom</hi> Jaſon <hi>hath received, and theſe all do contrary to the decrees of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>ſaying that there is another King, one</hi> Jeſus, <hi>and they troubled the people and the Rulers of the City when they heard theſe things;</hi> as you may read <hi>Acts</hi> 17.5,6,7,8.</p>
            <p>Whereby it appears firſt that ſome were againſt meeting and preaching in houſes, when ſuch Chriſtian religious meetings, and preaching in houſes were ſo apparently owned by Teſtimonies from Heaven. 2ly. That if God Almighty ſhould never ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and ſignally own ſuch Chriſtian religious meetings, and practices (as meeting and preaching in houſes) by never ſo clear and infallible Teſtimonies from Heaven, yet notwithſtanding ſome out of ignorance or wilfulneſs will be ready to contradict and oppoſe the ſame. 3ly. That they who were ſo oppoſit to the practices of the Apoſtles and Primitive Chriſtians for meeting and preaching in Houſes as aforeſaid, were unbelievers &amp; formal profeſſors who were moved with envy againſt them and their practices. 4ly. That thoſe unbelievers and formal profeſſors that were moved with envy againſt the true Goſpel, Preachers and Hearers did take unto them certain leud fellows of the baſer ſort and gathered a company; 1. to ſet the City in an uproar, 2. to aſſault the houſe where the Primitive Chriſtians were met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94771:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
3. to pull them out of the houſe and bring them unto the Rulers, and 4. when they had pulled out the Brethren and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians out of the houſe and brougt them and the man of the houſe unto the Rulers, they begun to accuſe them before the Magiſtrates; 1. for being come into their City after that manner; 2. for turning the world upſide down; 3. they accuſed <hi>Jaſon</hi> (the man of the houſe) for receiving of them; and 4. they accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them all for doing contrary to the decrees of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and laſtly the Magiſtrates were ready to hear them, or give credit to their Accuſations againſt the true Goſpel Miniſters and Primitive Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Now ſeeing that envy in the unbelievers was the moving cauſe of taking to them the baſer ſort of people, and certain lewd fellowes, to make ſuch an uproar, and pull out the brethren and primitive Chriſtians to bring them before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to render them odious, and worthy of puniſhment, in their apprehenſions, and that there was a Magiſtracy ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſuch things, againſt the ſervants and people of God; how may this inſtruct all true Chriſtians and Chriſtian Magiſtrates? utterly to abhor, deteſt, and reject, ſuch wicked, ungodly, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian examples and practiſes, as envy then moved, or may now move unto, in the unbelievers and baſer ſort of people, againſt the godly examples and practiſes of the primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and how may this induce all true Chriſtians and Chriſtian Magiſtrates, to tollerate, juſtifie and own, the example and practiſe of the true Goſpel Preachers and primitive Chriſtians, to preach, and pray, and perform ſervice to God; by the word and ſpirit of God as they did; in other places then Paviſh Churches and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els: <hi>for God that made the World and all things therein; ſeeing that he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, neither is worſhiped with Mens hands, as though he needed anything, ſeeing he giveth unto all life and breath, and all things:</hi> as the Apoſtle hath teſtified, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24,25.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, But when he which teſtified that God dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, neither is worſhiped with Mans hands, as aforeſaid, was a ſtrict zealous outward profeſſor, and unacquainted with God in the ſpirit, he was zealous for the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple, and for the worſhip performed therein, and could not endure meeting, and preaching in Houſes, and to hear the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94771:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
outward Temple cryed down; for he joyned with the chief Prieſts, and conſented with others to the death of <hi>Stephen,</hi> for doing the ſame, (or as you may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. <hi>chap. Acts</hi> 7.) and as for <hi>Saul</hi> he made havock of the Church, and entering into every Houſe, (where they uſed to meet together) and haleing out Men and Women, committed them to Priſon, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.1,2,3. Whereby it is evident that <hi>Saul</hi> before his converſion, and whilſt he was ignorant of Chriſt within, was againſt meeting and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Houſes, and zealous for the outward Temple, (as many old formal profeſſors, before their converſion in ignorance are) ſo that he could perſecute the people of God to death for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: (as many ſtich like thorough ignorance of the way of the Lord are now ready to do) 2. That old zealous profeſſors before their convertion, and inward acquaintance with Chriſt in the ſpirit, are the greateſt perſecuters of them that are moſt acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Chriſt Jeſus within in the ſpirit, and are moſt againſt meeting and preaching in Houſes, and are zealous for the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple, and Temple-worſhip, which God hath by his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles teſtified againſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.47,48. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24,25. is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and plain as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, They who were ignorant of Chriſt in themſelves, were moſt againſt meeting and preaching in houſes, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perſecuters of them in whom Chriſt Jeſus was manifeſt, ſo that they in whom Chriſt Jeſus was revealed did deny the outward Temple, and aſſembled together to preach and pray in houſes, and were moſt oppoſed and perſecuted by them that were moſt in an outward form of profeſſion, and ignorant of the life and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Chriſt Jeſus as aforeſaid, though Almighty God did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently own his people in meeting and preaching in houſes, by ſignal Teſtimonies from Heaven, as by the Scriptures aforeſaid, is evident and plain.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Though the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> before his Converſion, and whilſt he had not the Revelation of Chriſt in himſelf, did greatly eſteem of the outward Temple, and highly oppoſe meeting and Preaching in houſes, by <hi>making havock of the Church, entering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every houſe, and halling men and women committed them to Priſon, Acts</hi> 7.3. yet after his Converſion and when he had the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Chriſt in himſelf that he might be a Preacher of him; as it is written, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15,16,17. Then he preached down the outward
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94771:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Temple Worſhip; as you may read, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24,25. and he own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and practiſed Meeting and Preaching in Houſes, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.6,7,8. <hi>Acts</hi> 28.30,31. Whereby it is evident and plain that the beſt of the Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt, have preached down the outward Temple ſince Chriſts Aſcenſion, and have owned and practiſed meeting and preaching in Houſes, and the true Goſpel Miniſters ſaid, <hi>walk as ye have us for examples, Phil.</hi> 3.17. who did frequently meet and preach in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels; therefore to meet and preach in houſes is very juſtifiable by the example and practices of the Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians, and owned by ſignal Teſtimonies from Heaven, and ought not therefore to be condemned or forbidden by Men.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>MEetings barely and ſimply conſidered, as meetings upon the account of Religious exerciſe without an intent precedent to do ſome unlawful action or miſchief when they are aſſembled together is no offence (it ſeems) againſt Law, or puniſhable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: <note place="margin">Anno 16. Car 2. fol. 25 26.</note> For firſt the Title of the Act, <hi>is to prevent and ſuppreſs ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Conventicles;</hi> ſo that Conventicles or meetings for the ſervice of God are not to be prevented and ſuppreſſed by the ſaid Act, but ſeditious Conventicles are to be prevented and ſuppreſſed thereby. 2ly. The remedies or penalties provided by the ſaid Act, are <hi>againſt the growing and dangerous practices of ſeditious ſectaries and other diſloyal perſons;</hi> who under pretence of tender Conſciences do at their Meetings contrive Inſurrections as late experience hath ſhewed; ſo that thoſe are ſeditious ſectaries and <hi>diſloyal perſons</hi> againſt whom the penalties of the Act in that caſe are made and provided, <hi>who under pretence of tender Conſciences do at their meetings contrive Inſurrections</hi> as aforeſaid. Whereby it may appear that for perſons to meet and aſſemble together upon the account of Religious exerciſe to the number of five and above, beſides them of the houſhold in other manner then is allowed by the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is to meet and aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether under ſuch a pretence to contrive Inſurrections, or do ſome miſchievous actions, under ſo fair a pretence as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94771:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
For thirdly the tenor or execution of the Act, <note place="margin">Anno 16. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> is <hi>to prevent the miſchiefs which may grow by ſuch ſeditious and tumultuous meetings under pretence of Religious Worſhip:</hi> Whereby it is evident that the meetings puniſhable by the ſaid Act, are to be <hi>ſeditious &amp; tumultuous meetings,</hi> which tends to miſchievous actions; ſo that the manner of meeting muſt be a <hi>ſeditious</hi> and <hi>tumultuous</hi> manner, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enacted, done or performed at the meeting, muſt be teaching, or <hi>acting ſedition, inſurrection or miſchief,</hi> or elſe how is it puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the ſaid Act aforementioned.</p>
            <p>And as to the matter of fact againſt preaching perſons prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or to be reſtrained from coming within five miles of <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Towns Corporate,</hi> or within five miles of any <hi>Pariſh, Town,</hi> or place wherein they have been <hi>Parſons, Vicars, Curats, Stipendaries, Lecturers,</hi> poſſeſſed of any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Spiritual Promotions, &amp;c.</hi> is it not to be proved as matter of fact againſt ſuch preaching per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons prohibited and to be reſtrained as aforeſaid: Firſt, <hi>that they take upon them to preach without any right or authority from God;</hi> 2ly. <hi>that they preach contrary to the lawes and ſtatutes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> 3ly. <hi>that the meetings wherein they ſo preach are unlawful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles or Conventicles;</hi> 4ly. <hi>that ſuch preaching perſons have been poſſeſſed of ſome Eccleſiaſtical or ſpiritual promotions;</hi> 5ly. <hi>that they have been in holy Orders, or pretend to be in holy Orders in a National or Parochial way;</hi> 6. <hi>that they are ſetled perſons or have ſetled themſelves ſometimes by three or more in Corporations, thereby taking an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to diſtill the poyſonous principles of</hi> Schiſme <hi>&amp;</hi> Rebellion <hi>into the hearts of the people to the great danger of the Church and Kingdom;</hi> 7ly. What it is to preach contrary to the Lawes and Statutes of the Kingdom as to the matter of preaching, muſt it not be to preach Schiſme and Rebellion or inſurrection and ſedition, that is the matter puniſhable; becauſe preaching the Goſpel of Chriſt and the pure Word of God is not the matter of preaching forbidden.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written from a Principle of Truth, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and peace on the behalf of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and godly Preachers, and owned by</dateline>
               <signed>Chriſtian Moderation</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94771:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Something more by way of Addition and Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein alſo is anſwered ſome great Objections, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>NOw if Chriſtian Religious Meetings and Preaching in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels be accounted ſeditious Conventicles, becauſe of the manner of meeting and preaching, when both the matter and manner of meeting and preaching is according to the holy Scriptures, and the practice of the Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians, what juſt ground or reaſon from the holy Scriptures can be produced for the proof of the ſame to make perſons guilty of puniſhment, either by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, ſines or Baniſhment for ſo doing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Perhaps ſome may object or ſay its no matter though the holy Scriptures and practice of the Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians do allow of the manner of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Meeting and Preaching in upper Chambers and in private Houſes; ſo that there is no juſt ground or reaſon to be produced from the holy Scriptures or practice of the Apoſtles of Chriſt and Primitive Chriſtians to prove Chriſtian Regions Meetings and preaching (in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels) to be ſeditious Conventicles, and unlawful aſſemblies, when both the manner and matter of meeting and preaching is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the holy Scriptures; yet there is an Act (or Ordinance of Man) made againſt the ſame, and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Be ſubject to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake;</hi> and therefore by that Act or Ordinance they are puniſhable for meeting and preaching (in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels) according to our apprehenſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In anſwer thereunto we ſay, that foraſmuch as every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of man ought to be ſubmitted unto for the Lords ſake, how careful ought men (in Authority to be who profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtian Magiſtrates too) to enact and ordain nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Service and Worſhip of God but what is according to the mind, ſpirit and word of God; ſeeing that the motive to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94771:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſubjection to ſuch Ordinances of men is for the Lords ſake; and how can they be ſubmitted unto for the Lords ſake if they be contrary to the mind, ſpirit and word of God, becauſe the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 2.13,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,15,16.</note> who exhorts to ſubjection to the Ordinances of Men, upon that conſideration, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13,14,15,16.) was one of the firſt that denyed ſubjection to that Ordinance made againſt preaching, or was chiefly concerned in refuſing ſubjection to the command or ordinance of Men, when they commanded <hi>Peter</hi> (for one) to preach no more in the Name of Jeſus; for the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct 4.17,18,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,20.</note> could not ſubmit himſelf to ſuch a command or ordinance of men, for the Lords ſake when he knew it to be contrary to the mind and ſpirit of God in forbidding them to preach as aforeſaid; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may it not be concluded upon juſt grounds from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and practice of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, that they did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a ſubjection to the Ordinances of Men for the Lords ſake, when they (<hi>viz.</hi> mens Ordinances) were againſt preaching in the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, and in oppoſition to the requirings of God and contrary to the Word of the Lord; for when the Apoſtles of Chriſt were forbidden to preach, and commanded by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates then not to teach at all in the Name of Jeſus, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.17,18. they put the Magiſtrates to be their own Judges, concerning that thing; however they could not be ſubject unto them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame ſo as to give over preaching, becauſe God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it of them; for firſt the Apoſtles of Chriſt ſpoke to the Magiſtrates by way of enquiry to make them their own Judges (of their unreaſonableneſs and injuſtice) concerning the ſame, ſaying, <hi>whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you,</hi> (ſo as to give over preaching in the name of Jeſus, when you forbid us to preach) <hi>more then unto God, judge ye?</hi> Secondly, they ſpoke by way of affirmation and juſtification of preaching when the Magiſtrates forbad them to preach, and could not give over Preaching though men did prohibit them from preaching; (which may ſerve as an uſe of reproof to many hypocritical Prieſts of this Generation) for ſaid the true Goſpel Miniſters, (to the Magiſtrates who forbad them to preach) <hi>We cannot but ſpeak the thing which we have heard and ſeen;</hi> as by the Scriptures is evident and plain, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 4. from verſe the 1. to the 21.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Apoſtles of Chriſt and true Goſpel Preachers did never intend that Chriſtians and Believers in Chriſt ſhould be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94771:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
judged as ſeditious Sectaries, and puniſhed by Fines, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ' and Baniſhment, under pretence of being at ſeditious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, for meeting and preaching in houſes (or other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels) when both the manner of their meeting and matter of preaching is according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and mind of Chriſt Jeſus; for it was the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles to meet together with the Primitive Chriſtians, and preach in houſes and other places, then Pariſh Churches and Chappels; and the Apoſtles of Chriſt who had the mind of Chriſt Jeſus, commands us to walk as we have them for example, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. and muſt we be puniſhed for ſo doing? that is to ſay, for meeting and preaching in houſes, and out of houſes, as Chriſt and his Apoſtles and the Primitive Chriſtians did, ſeeing it was the practice of true Chriſtians and Miniſters of the Goſpel of Chriſt ſo to do, whoſe example is left upon record in Scripture; and they have given commandment to Chriſtians to walk as they have them for an example, whoſe godly meetings were lawful aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, how then can ſuch godly meetings be ſeditious Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which be according to ſuch good examples?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Now if any object and ſay that Preaching muſt not be in Houſes, but in the viſible Church of Chriſt Jeſus; in Anſwer thereunto we may ſay unto ſuch, <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>That the Pariſh meeting places are not the viſible Church of Chriſt Jeſus; firſt, becauſe the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ſaith, <hi>that the Church is the houſhold and family of God:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy on Good Friday, the Collects ſo called.</note> 2ly. That the whole body of the Church is governed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God, but ſo are not the Pariſh meeting places; how then can they be ſaid to be Chriſts viſible Church: For 3ly. it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> of both <hi>Provinces,</hi> and the whole Clergy in the <hi>Convocation</hi> holden at <hi>London,</hi> in the year 1562. in the 19<hi>th.</hi> Article of the Church, <note place="margin">Article 19.</note>
               <hi>that the viſible Church of Chriſt is a Congregation of faithful men, in the which the pure Word of God is preached:</hi> is not therefore the preaching of the pure word of God in a Congregation of faithful men, the preaching of it in the viſible Church of Chriſt as aforeſaid? though they be not met and aſſembled together in a Pariſh Church or a Chappel.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergie</hi> in that <hi>Convocation</hi> ſaid, and in the 13<hi>th.</hi> Article it is declared, <note place="margin">Article 13.</note>
               <hi>that works done before the Grace of Chriſt, and the inſpiration of his Spirit are not pleaſant to God:</hi> here they own inſpiration; and foraſmuch as preaching is a work, do not the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94771:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> own and declare in effect that none can preach aright ſo as to be well pleaſing unto God untill they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the ſpirit of God, (though they may preach in a Pariſh Church, or a Chappel.)</p>
            <p>In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 34<hi>th. Article</hi> they ſay, <note place="margin">Article 34.</note>
               <hi>that nothing is to be ordained againſt Gods Word:</hi> now then if any thing be ordained by men againſt the Worſhip of God, is not that ordained againſt Gods Word? Again in the 6. Article the Biſhops and Clergy have declared, <note place="margin">Article 6.</note>
               <hi>that whatſoever is not read in the Scriptures, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of the Faith, or to be thought requiſite or neceſſary to Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the ſame <hi>Convocation</hi> they have agreed and declared in the 20<hi>th.</hi> Article, <note place="margin">Article 20.</note>
               <hi>that it is not lawful for the Church to ordain any thing that is contrary to Gods Word written, and as it ought not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree any thing againſt the ſame; ſo beſides the ſame ought it not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force any thing to be believed for neceſſity of Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If nothing ought to be ordained that is contrary to the Word of God, <note place="margin">Article 34.</note> then if an Ordinance be made againſt meeting and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Houſes and upper Chambers, <note place="margin">Article 20.</note> (or in other places then Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches and Chappels) is not that Ordinance made againſt the Word of God, becauſe the holy Scriptures are ſaid to be the Word of God, againſt which nothing ought to be ordained as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; and by the holy Scriptures it is evident and plain, that it was the practice of the Primitive Chriſtians, and Apoſtles of Chriſt to aſſemble together and meet in private Houſes, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Chambers to Preach and Pray, and perform ſervice to God, and their practice is left upon record in Scripture, as a godly Chriſtian example for Believers to follow; and they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded true chriſtians to walk as they have them for an enſample, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>If it be not lawful for the Church of <hi>England</hi> to ordain any thing againſt the word of God written, <note place="margin">Article 34.</note> then if they ordain that Chriſtians muſt not meet and aſſemble together to preach and pray, <note place="margin">Article 6.</note> and performe ſervice to God in any place, but a Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh Church or a Chappel, is not ſuch an ordinance againſt the Word of God written? becauſe the Apoſtles of Chriſt ſaith to the Saints and Believers in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>walk as ye have us for an enſample:</hi> And they met together to preach and pray in Houſes and upper Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, (and not in Pariſh Churches and Chappels) for they preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94771:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
down the outward Temple, <note place="margin">Article 19.</note> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 7.41.47. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24,25.</p>
            <p>If the viſible Church of Chriſt be a Congregation of faithful men, in the which the pure Word of God is preached, and if none can preach the ſame, ſo as to be well pleaſing unto God before they be inſpired by the ſpirit of God, do not ſuch as be inſpired by the Spirit of God moſt truly preach the Word of God (though not in a Pariſh Church or a Chappel) and do not they come to the Church of Chriſt who meet and aſſemble toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Congregation of faithful men to hear the Word of God preached, by ſuch as are inſpired by the Spirit of God, as aforeſaid; <note place="margin">Article 34. Article 6. Article 20.</note> (though in other places then Pariſh Churches and Chappels) and if nothing ought to be ordained contrary to Gods word, is it not plain that every Ordinance of man which is to be ſubmitted unto for the Lords ſake, ſhould anſwer the mind of God by being according to the Word of God, as aforeſaid; becauſe the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergie</hi> in their <hi>Convocation</hi> have agreed and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>that it is unlawful for the Church to ordain any thing that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods Word written, and as they ought not to decree any thing againſt the Word of God, ſo beſides the ſame they ought not to enforce anything, as aforeſaid;</hi> as by the Scriptures and the ſaid Articles is evident and plain.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
